let's look at the solution to our
coherence definition quiz where we had
two cores running in a coherent system
executing some code and the question was
basically which of these five
possibilities for what gets printed are
possible let's see what can happen in
these two programs if core one gets to
go first with a equals one it's then
going to spin here for as long as X
equal one so it gets stuck until Core 2
does something eventually however core 2
we'll do a equals 0 in which case core 1
gets to continue and now core 1 we'll
set a to 1 korto will wait here until a
is set to 1 because as long as it's set
to 0 the way it set it is going to get
stuck here
so what then happens is core 1 when it
sets this release is called - now core 2
can do this and this first while core 1
is still being delayed here or it can be
that core 1 gets here first and then
core 2 gets here so definitely these two
outcomes are possible
they basically depend on after core 1
waits for Core 2 to release it and then
it itself releases core to who gets to
print first now let's see if it's
possible for core 1 to never get to this
point for that to happen core one needs
to get stuck here in this while loop
which means that a needs to stay 1
forever that can only occur if core 2 is
done with its program and the resulting
value of a is still one or if core to
also get stuck here and the resulting
value of a is still one so core 1 is
stuck here and a is 1 if that happens
before core 2 gets to a equals 0 then
core 2 is gonna release core 1 so a
equals 0 had to happen before this if a
equals 0 happened before all of this
then what happens is a equals 0 equals 1
now we're stuck waiting for 1 but core 2
will continue and it has
to see the one because this is a
coherent system eventually because
equals one happened after equals zero
Core 2 has to see the 1 and proceed once
it proceeds is going to set a 2-0 core
one has to see that because of the
second part of the definition and
proceed so it's not possible to get core
1 stuck here by just moving the a equals
0 to the beginning now let's see if it's
possible for Core 2 to finish the whole
thing before this happens in which case
core 1 will get stuck here but that's
not possible because core 2 now needs to
execute this whole program here before
core 1 even begins that's not possible
because core 2 sets a to 0 and then
waits for it to become nonzero so core
to cannot finish the whole thing until
core 1 does at least this at which point
we are back to the first case of pretty
much core 1 will eventually see that the
a is 0 because core to set it that way
after a became 1
it's also important to notice that it's
not possible for for example equals 1
and a equals 2 to happen one after the
other and then core one thinks that this
was the last right so it gets stuck here
while core 2 thinks this was the last
right and then gets stuck here because
the third part of the coherence
definition says that both of them have
to think that the same axis was the last
one so if they agree that this was the
last one then this core gets released
and then ends up releasing the first one
if they think this was the last access
then this core gets to be released and
releases the second one so either way
it's not possible to get any of the 3
printouts in an incoherent system it can
easily happen that you get these or any
of these other three so for example
nothing can be printed then by simply
storing one to the cache and then never
really checking anything else just
looping on the value in the cache here
meanwhile this one stores another value
in its own cache then just infinitely
space
on it and then you can get the other two
possibilities here by simply one of them
not being entirely incoherent so as you
can see a coherent system prevents some
of the behaviors that are possible
in an incoherent system but all the
behaviors that are possible in the
coherent system are also possible in an
incoherent one so coherence is allowed
in an incoherent system is just that
incoherent systems don't guarantee that
all their behaviors are going to be
coherent